A Guide to the Papers of James Langstaff Dunn, 1850-1906, n.d.
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
- Correspondence
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. December 7, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Hdqts. 2nd Division, 2nd Brigade, 12 A.C. near Wauhatchie, he includes high praise for General Joseph Hooker; and thinks if he had been let alone at Gettysburg, Lee would have been routed; has formed a group to study chemistry.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. December 16, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Mead headquarters, Wauhatchie, Tenn., Dunn describes departure for home of the 29th Pennsylvania bearing a flag with holes in it from Gettysburg, Wauhatchie, Lookout Mountain--"not as bright as when presented at Aquia Creek."
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. December 18, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Wauhatchie, he talks of Miss Goodman arriving to take care of her wounded brother and says "It does a fellow good to see a white woman down here in this snuff eating, snuff dipping, half civilized country."
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. December 21, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Wauhatchie, he describes a visit to the top of Lookout Mountain where he visited a "beautiful little village called Summerville;" thinks bill of fare for Christmas will be boiled pork, beans, bean soup, a raw onion for each, hard tack soaked in cold water, coffee with one small spoon of sugar per cup.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. December 23, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    Dunn writes that the 111th Regiment will go home in a few weeks and he hopes to go with them; argues with Brigades from the Cumberland who claim they took Lookout Mountain; says the 2nd Division, 12th A. C., supported by Whittaker's Brigade of the 4th A.C., were the only troops engaged.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. December 25, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Hdqts., 2nd Brigade, 2nd Division, 12 A.C., he describes a "pleasant time; " roast beef with soft bread with butter exchanged with "bitters" with an old native; have received orders to move back to Bridgeport; 111th Regiment of Pennsylvania is leaving for home but he doesn't think he can go.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. December 31, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Wauhatchie, he reviews his participation in the army's activities of the past year.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. April 1, 1864. (Folder 7.)
    From Louisville, Ky., Dunn relates an amusing story of a captain who voted for a Copperhead being put off the train.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. April 3, 1864. (Folder 7.)
    From Nashville, Tenn., he includes some comments on how Yankee business entrepreneurs have revitalized Nashville and comments on his visit to observe an inspection of a Negro regiment.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. April 7, 1864. (Folder 7.)
    From Bridgeport, Ala., Dunn reports that he is in the process of establishing a brigade hospital.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. April 9, 1864. (Folder 7.)
    Dunn reports that he is writing a few lines to pass away his first Sunday in camp since returning from home. He is well and enjoying himself in the spring weather, but sorry he had not stayed home longer. He comments that the camp is nicely situated on the south bank of the Tennessee River and the men are all healthy.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. April 20, 1864. (Folder 7.)
    From Bridgeport, Ala., he describes breaking up and reformation of brigades--12th Corps assigned to the 11th, which is primarily Dutch and "infernally cowardly;" decries the bad treatment of recruits at Camp Copeland.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. April 24, 1864. (Folder 7.)
    Dunn is glad to hear she received a box he sent with $200. He is in favor of her taking a trip to Philadelphia if she has company for the trip. It would be better to visit Philadelphia than Pittsburgh because he could see more in the former city in one day than in Pittsburgh for a month.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. May 9, 1864. (Folder 7.)
    From 2nd Brigade, 2nd Division, 20th A.C.--Hospital in the Field, he writes in the midst of the battle of Mill Creek Mountain [Rocky Face Ridge, part of the Atlanta Campaign] --up all night attending more than 200 wounded.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. May 21, 1864. (Folder 7.)
    From Camp near Cassville, Ga., (four miles from Atlanta), Dunn describes fighting, marching night and day with bayonets and butts of muskets principal weapons--"few bullet wounds but plenty of broken heads and black eyes;" 300 men killed and wounded in his division; Union army in chase toward Atlanta.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. June 11, 1864. (Folder 7.)
    From Camp near Lost Mountain, Ga, he writes they have been in camp four days resting from marching and fighting.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. June 26, 1864. (Folder 7.)
    Dunn writes he will be paid in a few days and will send her money so that she can pay off all her debts. They are making slow progress because they are required to keep up communications in the rear to a distance of 100 miles, and they must take time in flanking the enemy.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. June 30, 1864. (Folder 7.)
    From Hospital in the Field near Marietta, Ga., Dunn reports they have been under constant fire for the past six days with constant noise of cannon and musketry--"I begin to feel as if it would be almost heaven to get somewhere that I could be quiet once more."
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. July 15, 1864. (Folder 7.)
    From Camp near Chattahoochee River, he reports things are progressing rapidly--taking time and cleaning out the country--can see Atlanta from the camp.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. July 22, 1864. (Folder 7.)
    From Camp near Atlanta, Ga., mentions skirmish of three days in the center of the entire Army and ensuing bloody battle with complete victory; describes meeting Confederates marching from Atlanta with both armies taken by surprise--enemy gave way--over 500 men killed and wounded in Union Division; tells of occupation of Atlanta at daylight by 23rd Army Corps, with his corps following; found several Rebel women in men's clothing among the killed.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. July 30,1864. (Folder 7.)
    From Camp near Atlanta, includes sketch showing position; describes reaction of the troops to the transfer of General Joseph Hooker.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. August 11,1864. (Folder 7.)
    From Corps Hospital in the field, Dunn attributes failure thus far to take Atlanta to "some of the cavalry;" feels General Sherman "showed smallness" in treatment of Hooker.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. August 16,1864. (Folder 7.)
    From Division Hospital near Atlanta, reports he is tiring of the army, but discusses necessity of continuing, worries about transition to peace and if former prosperity ever will be regained; siege of Atlanta continues.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. September 7, 1864. (Folder 8.)
    From Hdqts. 2nd Brigade-Atlanta, he has entered Atlanta and is headquartered in an "aristocratic mansion;" is very well situated as to comfort; mentions that he borrowed paper on which he is writing from southerners to give an idea of poor quality they have been forced to use; describes attitudes and actions of "secesh" who have remained in the city.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. September 19, 1864. (Folder 8.)
    From Atlanta, he writes in detail of the departure of southerners and their families for the north, leaving all homes and many possessions behind; tells of purchasing a fine piano for $125 and valued at $1000 from a departing southerner; says the city will be occupied only by troops, with most southerners wanting the Governor of Georgia to surrender the whole state.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. September 25, 1864. (Folder 8.)
    From Atlanta, Dunn comments of the virtues of Generals Sheridan, Sherman, Grant and Kilpatrick and calls Generals McClellan and Fitz John Porter "deadbeats," discusses current political situation and strong desire for unconditional surrender.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. September 27, 1864. (Folder 8.)
    From Atlanta, Dunn describes meeting acquaintance just released from Andersonville prison; tells of burning of mansions and replacement with army buildings; says "this war will entirely ruin Georgia-the people outside our lines are now starving to death."
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. October 9, 1864. (Folder 8.)
    From Atlanta, he describes General (John Bell) Hoods military actions in harassing the rear of the Union in Atlanta in violation of an armistice between him and General Sherman--an action, he writes, which was "soundly defeated;" more details on the shipping of the piano.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. October 18, 1864. (Folder 8.)
    From Atlanta, predicts General Hood will attempt to move his army to reach Lee in Virginia; says scarcity of food in surrounding area probably will cause all to starve, with some families existing only on parched corn and sweet potatoes; thinks the only result can be "anarchy, discord, starvation, desolation, degradation and subjugation; describes his position as Brigade surgeon and says he wants to leave full service and return to a hospital.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. November 4, 1864. (Folder 8.)
    From Atlanta, Dunn describes his diet, saying that an onion is a luxury, with army rations being plentiful but boring; plans are afoot for army to burn Atlanta and leave it; more details on attempt to ship the piano, adding that it might have to be done piecemeal.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. November 5, 1864., Ink illegible for the most part. (Folder 8.)
    From Atlanta, says he wrote two letters a week but that there is great uncertainty whether mail carried by the Military Railroad reaches its destination. Makes some mention of a returned prisoner from Andersonville.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. November 8, 1864., Ink still very faded. (Folder 8.)
    From Atlanta, Ga., Dunn writes concerning election day, that he voted for peace, and reflects on life in the four years since the previous elections. They expect to move on the next day with 20 days rations in the wagon.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. December 20, 1864. (Folder 8.)
    From Camp near Savannah, Ga., he describes the march to Savannah which included the exodus of 20,000 slaves gaining freedom; says they "relieved our Southern Brethren of a large amount of both public and private property;" comments on the evils of slavery and "the cruel lash of the slave driver in a land that boasts of its extended freedom;" reports that the attack on Savannah is about to begin.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. December 22, 1864. (Folder 8.)
    From Savannah, he writes they entered the city on Dec 21 when Rebels decided to evacuate; elaborates on conditions in the city; says he will bring wife a "very nice little 12-year-old Negro girl" if she wants; thinks next move will be on Charleston; comments on the Rebels hate of the poor class of Irish and the Irish reactions.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. December 25,1864. (Folder 8.)
    Dunn wishes his wife a merry Christmas; wants wife and daughter to visit in Savannah so the girl can see something of the world; tells about General's Sherman's review of the army the previous day and the reaction of southerners still in the city.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. January 21, 1865. (Folder 9.)
    From Savannah, Dunn explains cause of mail delays as being attributed to all boats being pressed into service to carry troops; piano slowly reportedly making its way homeward; vents anger at treatment of northern prisoners.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. January 26, 1865. (Folder 9.)
    From Savannah, he writes that he receives orders to march the next day--in a brief addition reports march to Charleston now underway; severe criticism of some northern pandering to higher class southerners in Savannah.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. January 30, 1865. (Folder 9.)
    From Sister's Ferry, Ga., he says they left Savannah on the 26th and reached present location in a day.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. March 24, 1865. (Folder 9.)
    From Goldsboro, N.C., he writes that the troops entered Goldsboro on Jan 20th, with the campaign ended and General Sherman reporting the army will have six weeks rest; the march through South Carolina was a "perfect desolation--a cloud of smoke by day and a pillow of fire by night" over a broad belt of 70 miles rendered complete desolation; says it was a fixed determination of the soldiers to make South Carolina suffer despite efforts of the Generals to control the men; burning stopped when troops reached the North Carolina line; describes vividly the burning of Columbia, S.C.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. March 30, 1865. (Folder 9.)
    From Goldsboro, Dunn discusses his resignation plans, is aggravated with government's lack of fulfillment of duties to soldiers.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. April 15, 1865. (Folder 9.)
    From Washington, D.C., he writes he arrived in the city April 13 having been mustered out; describes turmoil in the city over Lincoln's assassination and says military authorities only "prevented the excited people from taking four or five hundred Rebel officers from prison and hanging them" gives opinions about the new President; plans to start for home next week.
  - William Dunn (brother) to James Langstaff Dunn. July 30, 1865. (Folder 9.)
    William Dunn writes from Nashville, Tenn., to his brother James Langstaff Dunn, in which he compliments James on his life as a doctor and reports that as he was responsible for the shipping, is glad that the piano got through.
  - Clara Barton to Dr. Dunn. September 22, 1865. (Folder 10.)
    Barton, the founder of the American Red Cross, writes to Dunn, "my old time cherished friend," renewing their acquaintance and inviting him to stop by when he visited her city. Included are a copy of the letter and a news clipping of a daguerreotype photograph of Clara Barton.
  - James van Voorst to "My Dear Joe." June 19, 1875. (Folder 11.)
    Van Voorst describes European travels and many concerts he has attended, both choral and band.
  - J. M. King to Dr. James L. Dunn. May 2, 1906. (Folder 12.)
    From Muncy, Pa., King reminiscences about old times in Conneantville,Pa., and requests photographs of Dunn's family.
  - Illegible letter n.d. (Folder 12.)
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. n.d. (Folder 12.)
    From headquarters, 1st Brigade, Sigle's Division, Kernstown, Va., Dunn talks of a small pox epidemic starting in his wife's community, discusses money matters and personal finances.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. n.d. (Folder 12.)
    From Washington, Va., headquarters, 1st brigade, Auger's division, Banks' corps, Dunn writes that General Pope had grand review of troops the previous Sunday, mentions have had a great amount of typhoid fever among some regiments in the 60th New York, some 600 cases, with deaths occurring every day; reports that he has been arrested and court-martialed for saying a certain colonel was " a d--n-ed fool", was cleared of the charges.
  - Illegible letter. n.d. (Folder 12.)
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn? n.d. (Folder 12.)
    In this partial letter, he says his watch chain was stolen out of his drawer while he was in Philadelphia; mentions that that he captured an ambulance and two good horses which he intends to carry baggage on with plans to sleep in the ambulance, says when he wants another horse he will give a cavalry soldier $5 to steal one, writes on with the following: "don't be frightened much if some of these mornings you see three or four hundred gray backs training up and down street for they are privileged characters. They just ride around our little army and take horses and clothing wherever they can find it and nobody says anything about it and do still less--General McClellan couldn't stand it any longer--he must go over to Philadelphia and get his wife to sooth his many cares, and while he is being soothed, the Rebels run over to old Pennsylvania for a drove of horses and got them. This is a H--l of a country, ain't it?"
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. Nov 16, n.y. (Folder 12.)
    Dunn discusses shooting death of Major Boyle, says army is living on hard tack, salt pork and an occasional ham.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn? n.d. (Folder 12.)
    Says jaundice is principal disease now, filling the hospitals and making many unfit for duty.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn? n.d. (Folder 12.)
    Dunn asks, "What great blessing has slavery conferred on the north that it should be so careful as to foster and preserve it? It first placed political parties almost in deadly conflict--it then divided the nation and trampled on the Nation's most sacred emblem--it's flag. The bloody battlefields before Richmond, the long and wearisome marches through the Valley of Virginia and the carnage of Bull Run and Antietam which has carried mourning throughout the whole north, dressed almost every household in crape. Yet to attempt to destroy the power that is doing all this is the rock on which our people of the north disgracefully split;" Dunn continues with more reflections upon slavery.
- Military Record of James Langstaff Dunn. May 1903. (Folder 13.)
  Compiled by the Soldiers and Sailors Historical and Benevolent Society.